A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Penitentiary, 1796-1991 (bulk 1906-1970)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Penitentiary, 1796-1991 (bulk 1906-1970)
The Library of Virginia
41558
211.47 cubic feet (698 boxes and 1 map case drawer) and 289 volumes
Virginia Penitentiary
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia, 2.2-3705.5), Virginia Government Data Collection and Dissemination Practices Act (Code of Virginia, 2.2-3800) and the Virginia Health Records Privacy Act (Code of Virginia, 32.1-172.1:03) establish guidelines for restricting access to medical and other confidential forms of information in order to protect personal privacy. Protected health information (PHI) as defined under the Privacy Regulations issued under the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) includes, but is not limited to, personally identifiable information such as names, addresses, and social security numbers. The Virginia Public Records Act (Code of Virginia, 42.1-78) includes a provision for closing all privacy protected information for 75 years from the date of creation. In accordance with this legislation, the Library of Virginia can and will restrict, in whole or in part, access to any privacy protected medical information or any other confidential information contained in these records
Restricted records in the Virginia Penitentiary collection may include but are not limited to: inmate medical records, inmate punishment records, execution files and records with social security numbers.
Acquisition Information
The Records of the Virginia Penitentiary came to the Library of Virginia in over 40 separate accessions. In July 2004, the Penitentiary records were combined into one accession (41558).
Accession 22801, Account Books, Criminal Charges, 1886-1903. Transfer information unavailable, accessioned 1948.
Accession 26162, Virginia Penitentiary, Board of Directors, Minutes, 1881-1942. Transferred from the Virginia Dept. of Welfare, 25 August 1964; accessioned 25 August 1964.
Accession 27951, Records, State Lime Grinding Plant No. 1, Staunton, 1914-1937. Transferred by Henry H. Budd, Dept. of Agriculture and Commerce, Division of Administration, Richmond, Va., 9 March 1973; accessioned 14 March 1973
Accession 27979, Rules and Regulations, 1802. Gift of Carroll Hart, Dept. of Archives and History, Atlanta, Georgia, 8 May 1973; accessioned 8 May 1973.
Accession 29347, Registers, Register Indexes, and Medical Registers, 16 volumes. Transferred from the Dept. of Corrections, 26 January 1977; accessioned 26 January 1977.
Accession 29399, Medical Registers, 1902-1965, 26 volumes. Transferred from the Virginia State Penitentiary, 26 April 1977; accessioned 25 February 1979.
Accession 30468, Death Register, 1926-1951, 1 volume. Transferred from the Virginia State Penitentiary, 30 June 1979; accessioned 30 June 1979.
Accession 30767, Fiscal Records, 1921-1970, 21 volumes. Transferred from the Dept. of Corrections, 14 February 1980; accessioned 21 May 1980.
Accession 30769, Inmate Index Cards, 1914, 1919, 1921-1949, 2 cubic feet. Transferred from the Dept. of Corrections, 21 February 1980; accessioned 21 May 1980.
Accession 30770, Register of Convicts, 1876-1884, 1 volume. Received from Greer Fullerton, Sr., Museum Coordinator. Academy for Staff Development, PO Box 2215, Waynesboro, Va, 10 September 1979.
Accession 31429, General Correspondence, 1890-1921. Gift of Paul W. Keve, School of Community Service, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Virginia, 8 June 1982; accessioned 21 June 1982.
Accession 31430, Penitentiary Registers and Ledgers, 1895-1972, 23 volumes. Gift of Paul W. Keve, School of Community Service, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Virginia, 8 June 1982; accessioned 21 June 1982.
Accession 31435, Letter, 1910. Gift of Paul W. Keve, School of Community Service, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Virginia, 8 June 1982; accessioned 24 June 1982.
Accession 31520, State Farm Records, 1956-1974, 13 items. Gift of Paul W. Keve, School of Community Service, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Virginia, 5 October 1982; accessioned 5 October 1982.
Accession 31816, Inmate Photographs and Negatives, 1914, 1934-1961. Transferred by Fleur L. Dorschel, File Maintenance and Storage, Dept. of Corrections, 24 June 1983; accessioned 30 June 1983.
Accession 31910, General Ledger and Journal Entries, 1974-1979. Transferred by Glenda J. Adams, Accounting Department, Virginia State Penitentiary, 14 October 1983; accessioned 26 October 1983.
Accession 33674, General Records, 1912-1963, 12 items. No acquistion information available; accessioned 1989.
Accession 35176, Ledgers and Registers, 43 volumes. Transferred by Julian V. Pugh, Central Criminal Records, Dept. of Corrections, 8 June 1981; accessioned 17 November 1997.
Accession 35177, Registers, 1902-1971, 4 volumes. No acquisition information available; accessioned 18 November 1997.
Accession 35178, Registers, 1865-1908, 1951-1956, 9 volumes. No acquisition information available; accessioned November 1997.
Accession 35179, Virginia Penitentiary, Board of Directors, Minutes, 1874-1877, 1 volume. No acquistion information available; accesioned 20 November 1997.
Accession 35180, Daybook, 1817-1818. Acquired prior to 1905. No acquisition information available; accessioned 21 November 1997.
Accession 35182, Virginia Penitentiary. Board of Inspectors, Proceedings, 1800-1803. Acquired prior to 1905. No acquisition information available; accessioned 24 November 1997.
Accession 35183, Transporation Checklist, 1879-1881, 1 volume. Acquired prior to 1905. No acquisition information available; accessioned 25 November 1997.
Accession 35184, Virginia Penitentiary. Board of Visitors, 1807-1816. Acquired prior to 1905. No acquisition information available; accessioned 25 November 1997.
Accession 37333, Papers, 1823-1841. No acquisition information available; accessioned 23 May 2000.
Accession 37432, Superintendent's Records, 1893-1966, 40.2 cu. ft. and 1 volume. Transferred by J.P. Mitchell, Warden, State Penitentiary, Richmond, Virginia, 28 August 1979; accessioned 30 June 2000.
Accession 37440, Records, 1972-1980, 12 volumes. Transferred by Paul Keve, Virginia Commonwealth University, 30 June 1982; accessioned 11 July 2000.
Accession 37475, Accounts with A. and S. H. Smith, Agents at Staunton, 1811-1814. No acquisition information available; accessioned 21 July 2000.
Accession 37489, Papers concerning Board of Visitors, prisoners, prison conditions and investigations, and penitentiary finances, 1798-1824. Acquired prior to 1905. No acquisition information available; accessioned 25 July 2000.
Accession 37539, Penitentiary construction papers, 1797-1799. No acquisition information available; accessioned 9 August 2000.
Accession 37567, Miscellaneous records, 1812-1863. No acquisition information available; accessioned 16 August 2000.
Accession 37603, Inmate Negatives, 1934-1938, 2.88 cu. ft.. No acquisition information available; accessioned 21 August 2000.
Accession 37685, Daybook, 1933-1940, 1 volume. No acquisition information available; accessioned 21 September 2000.
Accession 37686, Letter book, 1895-1903, 1 volume. No acquisition information available; accessioned 22 September 2000.
Accession 37688, Monthly Reports, 1892-1912, 1 volume. No acquisition information available; accessioned 27 September 2000.
Accession 37718, Accounts and invoices of goods manufactured at the penitentiary, 1864-1865. No acquisition information available; accessioned 25 October 2000.
Accession 37722, Indexes, 2 volumes. No acquisition information available; accessioned 26 October 2000.
Accession 37723, Index, 1 volume. No acquisition information available; accessioned 26 October 2000.
Accession 37725, Indexes to Prisoner Registers, 3 volumes. No acquisition information available; accessioned 26 October 2000.
Accession 38067, General Records, 1865-1950, 41 cu. ft. No acquisition information available; accessioned 8 June 1982.
Accession 38101, Appointments of Keeper, 1796-1819. No acquisition information available; accessioned 17 May 2001.
Accession 38103, Execution Files, 1908-1970, 5.63 cu. ft. No acquisition information available; accessioned 17 May 2001.
Accession 38104, Reports, 1903-1984, 1.45 cu. ft. No acquisition information available; accessioned 17 May 2001.
Accession 38106, Financial Records, 1880-1980, 14 cu. ft. and 29 volumes. No acquisition information available; accessioned 17 May 2001.
Accession 38107, Records, 1906-1937, 16.5 cu. ft. No acquisition information available; accessioned 17 May 2001.
Accession 38108, Glass Plate Negatives of Convicts, 1906-1914, 19 cu. ft. No acquisition information available; accessioned 17 May 2001.
Accession 38109, Superintendent's Correspondence, undated, 0.375 cu. ft. No acquistion information available; accessioned 17 May 2001.
Accession 38110, Inmate Photographs, 1965-1966, 1 volume. No acquisition information available; accessioned 17 May 2001.
Accession 38214, Treatment Register, 1910-1920, 1 volume. No acquisition information available; accessioned 12 July 2001.
Accession 38651, Records, 1873-1990, 10 cu. ft. and 7 volumes. Transferred by Paul Henick, Dept. of Corrections, Richmond, Va., 30 November 2001; accessioned 30 November 2001.
Accession 40350, Index Cards, 1917-1965, 2.04 cu. ft. No acquisition information available; accessioned 18 February 2003.
Accession 41991, Prisoner photographs, negatives and interpositives, 1938-1961. Records duplicated from originals held by Library of Virginia by Northeast Document Conservation Center, 2005-2007.
Accession 42742, Raymond Muncy records, 1987-1991. Gift of R.M. Oliver, Richmond, Va., 14 July 2006; accessioned 14 July 2006.
Alternative Form Available
Prisoner Registers and Indexes, 1865-1980, also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reels 5989-6004
Historical Information
In December 1796 the Virginia General Assembly passed legislation authorizing the construction of a penitentiary and providing details on its design and operation. Governor James Wood (1796-1799) selected Benjamin Henry Latrobe as architect and Thomas Callis as superintendent of the project. A twelve acre plot of land on the James River just outside of Richmond was purchased and construction began in 1797.
The Virginia Penitentiary opened in 1800. Latrobe's design, while architecturally impressive, was functionally flawed. The cells were large enough to hold several prisoners. However, the cell doors had no windows making it impossible to supervise the prisoners. In addition, the cells had no heat, poor ventilation and no plumbing. Prisoners also had to eat in these conditions since the penitentiary did not have a dining room. The penitentiary's day-to-day operation was overseen by a Keeper (or Superintendent), appointed by the Governor for a one year term, and deputies appointed by the Keeper. A board of twelve inspectors, appointed by the Hustings Court of the City of Richmond, oversaw penitentiary operations. In 1819 the General Assembly abolished the Board of Inspectors and created a five person Board of Directors (later reduced to three members) who were appointed by the governor; the Keeper was still appointed by the governor. An 1852 act gave the General Assembly the power to elect a superintendent for a two year term. The 1902 Constitution expanded the Board of Directors to five members and empowered the Board, not the General Assembly, to select the Superintendent for a four year term.. In 1942 the Virginia General Assembly created the Virginia Department of Corrections, consolidating the administration and regulation of all penal and correctional intuitions under one agency lead by the Commissioner of Corrections. This new department was overseen by a five member Board of Corrections. Corrections departments were merged into the Department of Welfare and Institutions by a government reorganization act passed by the General Assembly in 1948. In 1974 the Department of Welfare and Institutions was abolished and a new Department of Corrections was created.
Two of the most influential superintendents were Evan F. Morgan (1906-1909) and Rice M. Youell (1922-1942). In 1906 Morgan established the State Convict Road Force to assist the new State Highway Commission build roads in Virginia. Beginning in 1908, all executions were centralized at the Virginia Penitentiary. Morgan oversaw the installation of the electric chair and established procedures for executions. Youell was the longest serving of any superintendent at the Virginia Penitentiary. He served as superintendent from 1922 to 1942. During this tenure he greatly expanded educational and vocational opportunities for inmates. He successfully transitioned the Penitentiary's industries to meet the requirements of the federal Hawes-Cooper Convict Labor Act of 1929. This legislation prohibited the interstate sale of prison goods and went into effect in 1934. The General Assembly passed legislation in 1934 which established the state-use principle regarding prison products created by convict labor. The law specified that prison industries should only produce items needed by state agencies or political subdivisions. Youell was selected as the first Commissioner of Corrections in 1942. In 1948 he was named director of the reorganized corrections division, a position he held until his retirement in 1960. Major Youell was elected president of the American Prison Association in 1937 and president of the Southern States Prison Association in 1955.
Latrobe's original structure was torn down in 1928. The Virginia Penitentiary closed in December 1990 and was torn down in 1992.
Scope and Content
The Virginia Penitentiary collection contains a wide variety of bound volumes and paper records spanning nearly 200 years (1796-1991; bulk 1906-1970). Included are administrative records such as annual reports, correspondence, office and subject files, minute books, photographs, blueprints, as well as specific records related to the State Convict Road Force and State Convict Lime Grinding Board. Also included are financial records such as account books, cash books, ledgers, payrolls, and receipt books. The prisoner related records include: prisoner registers, photographs and negatives, medical records, commitment orders, punishment records, escape reports, index cards and execution files. The records of the Virginia Penitentiary document the institutions' operational history, prisoners and the evolution of corrections in Virginia.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Penitentiary Papers, 1796-1865
Subseries A. Penitentiary Construction Papers, 1797-1799
Subseries B. Letters of Application and Recommendation for Positions of Penitentiary Keeper, Agent and Physician, 1796-1797, 1812-1916 and 1819
Subseries C. Board of Inspectors and Visitors, 1800-1820
Subseries D. Prisoners, 1798-1820
Subseries E. Prison Conditions and Investigations, 1800-1824
Subseries F. Penitentiary Financial Records, 1800-1865
Series II. Prisoner Records, 1865-1990
Subseries A. Registers, 1865-1990
Subseries B. Photographs and Negatives, 1906-1961, 1965-1966
Subseries C. Penitentiary Commitment Orders, 1865-1896
Subseries D. Inmate Index Cards for Felons, 1914, 1919, 1921-1949
Subseries E. Execution Files, 1908-1970
Series III. Board of Directors (State Prison Board), 1874-1877, 1881-1942
Subseries A. Minutes, 1874-1877, 1881-1942
Subseries B. Correspondence and Reports, 1902-1939
Subseries C. Annual Reports, 1877-1942
Series IV. Office of the Superintendent, 1869-1991 (bulk 1908-1970)
Subseries A. Letter Books, ca. 1871-1906
Subseries B. General Correspondence, 1892-1991 (bulk 1908-1970)
Subseries C. State Convict Road Force, 1906-1940
Subseries D. Correspondence, Office of the Governor, 1915-1916, 1921-1940
Subseries E. Reports and Publications, 1921-1982 (bulk 1941-1982)
Subseries F. Guard Logs, Virginia Penitentiary, 1972-1980
Subseries G. Reference Books, 1869-1931
Subseries H. Photographs, 1976-1989 (bulk 1976-1979)
Series V. State Convict Road Force, 1904-1965 (bulk 1906-1949)
Subseries A. Prisoner Records, 1904-1965 (bulk 1910-1949)
Subseries B. Diaries, 1936-1938
Subseries C. Correspondence, 1910, 1912, 1919-1930, 1933-1941
Subseries D. Financial Records, 1906-1937
Series VI. State Convict Lime Grinding Board, 1914-1934, 1937 (bulk 1914-1922)
Subseries A. Minutes, 1914-1921, 1923
Subseries B. Correspondence, 1914-1925
Subseries C. Financial Records, 1914-1924
Subseries D. Records from the Dept. of Agriculture and Commerece, 1914-1934, 1937
Series VII. Financial Records, 1879-1881, 1884-1980 (bulk 1895-1933)
Series VIII. Blueprints and Drawings, 1940-1984
Contents List
- Series I. Penitentiary Papers, 1796-1865., Extent: 3.95 cubic feet of records. (Box 1-8., Box 1.)
  The Penitentiary Papers series is housed in nine (9) boxes with oversized material separated out and is arranged into seven (7) subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. Penitentiary Construction Papers; B. Letters of Application and Recommendation for Position of Penitentiary Keeper, Agent and Physician; C. Board of Inspectors and Visitors; D. Prisoners; E. Prison Conditions and Investigations; and F. Penitentiary Financial Records. This series consists of accounts, affidavits, contracts, deeds, letters (correspondence), minutes, muster rolls, petitions, plats, proceedings, reports and vouchers. This is an artificial series consisting of extant pre-1865 Penitentiary related records. During the evacuation of Richmond in April 1865, Penitentiary Superintendent Colin Bass carried off most of the penitentiary records and very few pre-1865 penitentiary records survive. Many of the records in this series were removed at some point from other collections such as the Office of the Governor and Auditor of Public Accounts. Additional records from the antebellum era related to the penitentiary may be found in the records of the Auditor of Public Accounts, General Assembly (especially Legislative Petitions and Executive Communications) and Office of the Governor. Published annual reports of the Directors of the Penitentiary as well as legislative reports on the Penitentiary from the antebellum period can be found in the Journal of the House of Delegates [J87 v6].
  - Series I. Subseries A. Penitentiary Construction Papers, 1797-1799. (Box 1 and Oversize Box 1.)
    This subseries is housed in 11 folders and contains correspondence and records related to the construction of the Virginia Penitentiary. Benjamin Henry Latrobe was named architect and Thomas Callis as superintendent of the project. Included is a survey of 12 acres in Henrico County and Richmond City for a penitentiary site (30 March 1797) and a petition of eight Richmond inhabitants against the proposed location of the penitentiary (1797). Thomas Callis also writes to Governor James Wood accepting appointment as superintendent of the project (16 April 1797). Callis enters into a contract with Martin Mims to supply 600,000 bricks for the penitentiary (21 July 1797). Benjamin Latrobe's correspondence with Governor Wood and the Council of State include offering his services for the penitentiary (25 January 1797) and acknowledgment of receipt of payment for his services (12 May 1797, 20 July 1797). Latrobe periodically reports on topics including general progress report (6 July 1797), water supply and well shaft (13 July 1797, 19 October 1797 and 26 October 1797), brick work (15 July 1797, 19 July 1797 and 22 August 1797), state of the walls, arches, brick work and delivery of materials (17 August 1797) and an estimate for the tunnel to carry water to the penitentiary and the number of bricks needed to complete the building (29 September 1797). Latrobe also asks the Governor for permission to temporarily retain the book of drawings for the penitentiary in order to copy them (5 October 1797). Additional Latrobe and Callis correspondence highlight their dispute over John Shortis' bill for work on the penitentiary and their supervisory responsibilities. Latrobe provides his account of the Shortis' conflict in letters to the Council of State (31 August 1797) and John Courtney (9 September 1797). Latrobe also writes Callis and informs him of his plans to inform the Council of Callis' incapacity as Superintendent (26 August 1797) and Callis' reply (27 August 1797).
    - Deed, Charles Boush and wife to Governor James Wood on behalf of the Commonwealth of Virginia, recorded 18 July 1797 (tract of land in Norfolk County, 10 acres, for Quarantine Hospital) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Survey of 12 acres in Henrico County and Richmond City for Penitentiary site; land purchased from Thomas Rutherford, 30 March 1797. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Petition by eight Richmond inhabitants against the proposed location of the Penitentiary, 1797. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter, Thomas Eddy of New York to [Governor James Wood] regarding the penitentiary (see Oversize Box 1, Folder 1a), 23 April 1797. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letter, Thomas Eddy of New York to [Governor James Wood] regarding the penitentiary, 23 April 1797. (Box 1, Folder 1a)
    - Letter, Thomas Callis to Governor James Wood, accepting appointment as Superintendent of the building of the penitentiary house, 16 April 1797. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Contract, Thomas Callis, state appointed "contractor", with Martin Mimms, the latter to lay 600,000 bricks in the gateway, foundations, and cellar stories of the penitentiary, 21 July 1797. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters written by Benjamin Henry Latrobe, architect of the penitentiary, regarding construction of same, 1797. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters written by Benjamin Henry Latrobe, John Shortis, carpenter, and Thomas Callis, regarding the bill presented by Shortis for work done on the penitentiary building, 1797. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence regarding the cost and purchasing of materials for the penitentiary, 1797. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Proposals and bids for construction work on the penitentiary building, 1797-1799. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Account of work done on the penitentiary building, 1797-1798. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Series I. Subseries B. Letters of Application and Recommendation for Positions of Penitentiary Keeper, Agent and Physician, 1796-1797, 1812-1816 and 1819. (Box 1-2.)
    This subseries is housed in 23 folders and contains correspondence related to the appointment of Penitentiary Keeper, Agent and Physician. During the antebellum years, the penitentiary keeper (later superintendent) was elected annually by the General Assembly. Abraham Douglass, who had served since 1807, left the position in 1812 and William Campbell replaced him. Campbell served until 1816 and was replaced by Samuel P. Parsons, a member of the Board of Inspectors. Records in this subseries include letters of application for the positions of Keeper, Agent and Physician, and letters and petitions of support for individual candidates sent to Governors James Barbour and Wilson Nicholas and members of the Council of State in 1812, 1813 and 1816. Applicants for Penitentiary Keeper include: Richard Armstrong, Edward Cahill, Robert Courtney, Thomas Drake, John Kelso, David Lewis, Joseph Mayo, Abijah Price, Ellis Puryear, Henry Shore, Lambert Smyth, Lewis Sowell, William D. Taylor, John Wright and George Wyatt. Applicants for Penitentiary Agent include: James A. Campbell, Samuel S. Carter, Samuel Lemaine, Thomas Staples, Philip Triplett and Stephen Woodson.
    - Letters of application and recommendation for position of penitentiary keeper and agent, 1796-1797 and 1812-1813. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letters of application and recommendation for position of penitentiary keeper and agent, 1816. (Box 1, Folder 13)